Inventory of the Rosemary Sprague Collection 1922-1991
Longwood University
Greenwood Library, Longwood Universtiy
Rosemary Sprague Collection 1922-1992
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2007.109
59 boxes
The collection consists of 59 boxes of materials related to the life and career of Dr. Rosemary Sprague. Among this collection are correspondence, writings, personal and biographical materials including a collection of photographs, and a collection of miscellaneous materials.
Rosemary Sprague, 1922-1991
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Longwood University in 1991.
Biographical Note
Rosemary Sprague was a graduate of Bryn Mawr College and received her master's degree and doctorate from Case Western Reserve University. She also studied at the Shakespeare Institute, Stratford-on-Avon, and at Oxford University and the University of London. She taught English at Longwood from 1962 until her retirement in 1990. She was promoted to full professorship in 1965, and two years after that she became Longwood's first Board of Visitors Distinguished Professor. She was the author of nine historical novels for young adults, biographies of Robert Browning and George Eliot, and a study of five American poets entitled Imaginary Gardens and the Sesquicentennial History of Longwood College. Dr. Sprague was an accomplished actress who loved the theatre her entire life. Prior to teaching at Longwood, she was Director of Dramatics at Notre Dame College. In 1971, Dr. Sprague established the Victorian Institute in collaboration with two colleagues from the University of North Carolina. The Institute has developed into an international literary society. During her lifetime, she was involved in teaching, writing, acting, professional organizations, and community-based groups; but today, her legacy lives on in her writings that are still held in libraries throughout the country.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 59 boxes of materials related to the life and career of Dr. Rosemary Sprague. Among this collection are correspondence, writings, personal and biographical materials including a collection of photographs, and a collection of miscellaneous materials.
The collection is divided into the following series: Series I: Correspondence, Series 2: Manuscripts (published and unpublished writings, transcripts of lectures, and research notes), Series 3: Personal & Biographical Materials (including a large collection of photographs) Series 4: Miscellaneous Materials (includes ephemera, memorabilia, and items of personal interest).
Correspondence: This series includes seven boxes that are subdivided into the following categories: Correspondence with illustrator J. B. Lankes (1986-1991), Correspondence with Western Case University professor and writer Horace Abram Rigg (1969-72), Business correspondence with publishers, Other business correspondence and Correspondence with family and friends.
Manuscript Collection: This series contains notes related to the research of her published writings as well as numerous drafts of these works including galley proofs and sample book jackets. The materials are arranged alphabetically by title of the work. Contained in this series are unpublished writings and transcripts of her lectures.
Personal and Biographical Materials: This collection includes a large number of photographs that span her lifetime providing glimpses into her family background and childhood years. There are also documents related to her academic career and personal involvements. In addition, there are newspaper articles that span Sprague's lifetime revealing much about her youth and her involvements. Included is a large box containing printed materials and three-dimensional personal items collected by Sprague.
Miscellaneous Materials: Contained in this collection are memorabilia such as post cards and playbills. The bulk of the collection consists of miscellaneous print materials that were of interest to Sprague.
Arrangement of Materials
The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Longwood University --Faculty and Staff
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence
Topical Term:
Authors, American--Correspondence.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: Correspondence
  - Correspondence with J. B. Lankes, (1986-1988)
    - 1986 Correspondence #1 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - 1986 Correspondence #2 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - 1987 Correspondence #1 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - 1987 Correspondence #2 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - 1987 Correspondence #3 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - 1987 Correspondence #4 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - 1987 Correspondence #5 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - 1988 Correspondence #1 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - 1988 Correspondence #2 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence with J. B. Lankes (1989-1991)
    - 1989 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:1)
    - 4/29/88 - 1/6/89 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:2)
    - 1990 Correspondence #1 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - 1990 Correspondence #2 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - 1/29/89- 1/20/90 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:5)
    - 2/ 27/90-9/17/90 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:6)
    - 1990 Correspondence - Lankes with Rosemary Sprague (Box-folder 2:7)
    - 1991 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:8)
    - 6/8/90 - 2/22/91 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:9)
    - 3/ 11/91 - 9/3/91 Correspondence (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Personal letters between Rosemary Sprague and J.B. Lankes (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Correspondence between J.B. Lankes and Minnesota Libraries (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Letters between J.B. Lankes and Longwood College about (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Correspondence with Horace Abram Rigg, Jr. (1969-1972)
    - May 28, 1969-October 13, 1969 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - August 6, 1969- February 23, 1969 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - March 3, 1969- May 22, 1969 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - October 13, 1969-December 19, 1969 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - January 6, 1970-April 28, 1970 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - April 29, 1970-January 28, 1972 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Correspondence with Publishers (1964-1976)
    - Chilton (1963-1978) (Box-folder 4:1-4)
    - Crowell (1963-1976) (Box-folder 4:5-8)
    - Dutton (1951) (4:9)
    - Horn Book Magazine (Box-folder 4:10)
    - John C. Winston (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Toni Strassman (1950-1951) (Box-folder 4:12-15)
    - Walck (1964-1971) (Box-folder 4:16-18)
    - Every Woman's Magazine (1951) (Box-folder 4:19)
    - Miscellaneous (1964-1967) (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence Related to the Publication of Imaginary Gardens
    - Imaginary Gardens #1 (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Imaginary Gardens #2 (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Imaginary Gardens #3 (Box-folder 5:3)
    - Imaginary Gardens #4 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Other Business Correspondence
    - Assisted Coal Industry Papers (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Correspondence with Rosalind Ivan (Box-folder 6:2)
    - Correspondence with Charles O'Brien Kennedy (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Correspondence with Burns Mantle (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Correspondence with Nada Prodauovié (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Correspondence with the Society of Stoopnocracy (Box-folder 6:6)
    - Letters from members of the Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Letters and Postcards from Oscar Williams (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Miscellaneous Business Correspondence (Box-folder 6:9)
    - Longwood Contracts (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Longwood Administration (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Correspondence Related to Victorian Institute (Box-folder 6:12)
    - College and University Correspondence (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Letters from Students (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Correspondence with Family, Friends and Longwood Alumni
    - Letters from Neville Coghill of Merton College, Oxford (1964-1967) (Box-folder 7:1)
    - Correspondence between Nivvy Erwin and Rosemary ((1944) (Box-folder 7:2)
    - Letters and postcards from Oscar Williams (1954-1963) (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Letters related to school, scholarships, death of her father, New York (1940s) (Box-folder 7:4)
    - Letters related to school, writing and acting (1950s) (Box-folder 7:5)
    - Letters from friends and acquaintances (1960s) (Box-folder 7:6)
    - Letters from friends and acquaintances (1970s) (Box-folder 7:7)
    - Letters from friends and acquaintances (1970s) (Box-folder 7:8)
    - Letters from friends and colleagues (1990s) (Box-folder 7:9)
    - Correspondence with family and friends, updated (Box-folder 7:10)
    - Letters of condolence received after death of Eleanor Sprague's husband, Percy (1943) (Box-folder 7:11)
    - Letters from Rosemary (1940s-1970s) (Box-folder 7:12)
    - Letters to Eleanor Sprague from other family members (1930s-1950s) (Box-folder 7:13)
    - Letters addressed to Eleanor and Rosemary (1930s-1950s) (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Collection of cards and printed items from friends (Longwood years) (Box-folder 7:15)
    - Collection of miscellaneous print items including invitations, brochures, notes (Box-folder 7:16)
    - Letters from Longwood students (1960s-1970s)\ (Box-folder 7:17)
- Series 2: Manuscripts
  - Published Works
    - Conquerers of Time - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 8:1-38)
    - Faith and Fandango - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 9:1-11)
    - Forever in Joy - handwritten draft (Box-folder 10:1-26)
    - Forever in Joy - typescript, annotated with corrections (Box-folder 11:1-13)
    - George Eliot: A Biography - 3 folders and a collection of unfoldered legal pads containing handwritten draft of book (Box 12)
    - George Eliot: A Biography - draft copy in typescript with edits (Box-folder 13:1-10)
    - Golden Keys - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 14:1-39)
    - Golden Keys - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 15:1-6)
    - " Heirs of Kiloran - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 15:1-7)
    - " Heroes of the White Shield - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 16:8-15)
    - Imaginary Gardens - draft copy in typescript with edits and annotations Edna St. Vincent Millay and Marianna Moore (Box-folder 17:1-17)
    - Imaginary Gardens - Section about Emily Dickinson, preliminary research and draft in typescript with edits and annotations (Box-folder 18:1-12)
    - Imaginary Gardens - Lowell Section, preliminary research and draft of section in typescript with edits and annotations (Box-folder 19:1-17)
    - Imaginary Gardens - Teasdale Section, preliminary research and draft of section in typescript (Box-folder 20:1-31)
    - The Jade Pagoda - draft copy and notes, handwritten (Box-folder 21:1-11)
    - The Jade Pagoda - draft copy in typescript with edits (Box-folder 22:1-15)
    - The Jade Pagoda - draft copy in typescript with edits (Box-folder 23:1-7)
    - A Kingdom to Win - draft copy and notes, handwritten (Box-folder 24:1-9)
    - Longwood College: A History - Drafts I and II in typescript (Box-folder 25:1-29)
    - Longwood College: A History - Draft III in typescript (Box-folder 26:1-26)
    - Longwood College: A History - Draft IV in typescript (Box-folder 27:1-27)
    - Longwood College: A History - galley proof (Box-folder 28:1-25)
    - Longwood College: A History - fragments of notes and research (Box-folder 29:1-25)
    - Red Lion and Gold Dragon - draft copy in typescript with edits (Box-folder 30:1-40)
    - Red Lion and Gold Dragon - draft copy in typescript (Box-folder 31:1-19)
    - Witch of Windsor - draft in typescript with notes (Box-folder 32:1-23)
    - Witch of Windsor - draft in typescript (Box-folder 33:1-8)
    - Witch of Windsor - draft in typescript (Box-folder 34:9-17)
    - Published story One Enchanted Visit in Everywoman's Magazine December 1951 (Box-folder 35:1)
    - Adaption of the play, The Satin Slipper(for Notre Dame performance) (Box-folder 35:2-10)
  - Unpublished writings
    - Unpublished Writings -- Larger works
      - A Beau for Aunt Mathilde (Box-folder 36:1-3)
      - From Ancient Britain to Tudor England (Box-folder 36:4-7)
    - Unpublished Writings --Short Stories
      - The Ballade (Box-folder 37:1)
      - The Descendant (Box-folder 37:2)
      - Giving a Tea (Box-folder 37:3)
      - A History of Thanksgiving (Box-folder 37:4)
      - The Light (Box-folder 37:5)
  - Research, Notes and Miscellaneous Materials and Fragments of Writings Related to Biographical Works
    - Robert Browning (Box-folder 38:1-5)
    - Robert Browning and Marianne Moore (Box-folder 38:6)
    - Robert Burns (Box-folder 38:7-8)
    - Emily Dickinson (Box-folder 38:9-11)
    - Ellen Glasgow (Box-folder 38:12-14)
    - Ellen Glasgow continued (Box-folder 39:1)
    - Edna Vincent St. Millay (Box-folder 39:2-3)
    - Marianne Moore (Box-folder 39:4)
    - Collection of miscellaneous note cards and notebooks containing research-related information used in writing publications (Box 40)
    - Andrew Lang Lecture Series (1954-1955) handwritten pages from small notebook (Box-folder 41:1-18)
  - Collection of Miscellaneous Lectures
    - Autobiographical (Box-folder 42:1)
    - Biography, the Other Face of the Coin (Box-folder 42:2)
    - Blush of Shame ... or Art is a Beautiful Thing (Box-folder 42:3)
    - Robert Browning (Topic of Lecture) (Box-folder 42:4)
    - Camelot (Box-folder 42:5)
    - Darkness at Noon (Box-folder 42:6)
    - The Dean's Watch Lecture given for Waterworks Players (Box-folder 42:7)
    - Education in Early America (topic of lecture) (Box-folder 42:8)
    - George Eliot (topic of lecture) (Box-folder 429)
    - Golden Keys lecture given in 1953. (Box-folder 42:10-11)
    - Hamlet (lecture about play) (Box-folder 42:12)
  - Collection of Miscellaneous Lectures (continued)
    - And Ladies of the Club - a book by Helen Santmeyer (Box-folder 43:1)
    - Longwood Commencement Speech given May 1979 (Box-folder 43:2)
    - Longwood -- writing the history of Longwood College (Box-folder 43:3)
    - Ode to Presentation of a Cake for Longwood Celebration (Box-folder 43:4)
    - The Saints -- Sinners Revised and Edited (Box-folder 43:5-6)
    - Revolutionary War lecture titled Through Rose Colored Glasses (Box-folder 43:7)
    - Shady Ladies Speech (Box-folder 43:8)
    - Sprague speaking on her publications (Box-folder 43:9)
    - Swinburne: After A Century" (Box-folder 43:10)
    - Thriller novels/fiction of the 20th Century (literary lecture) (Box-folder 43:11)
    - Two Hundred Years of Commercial Conspiracy (Box-folder 43:12)
    - Tuchman's "Guns of August" (literary lecture) (Box-folder 43:13)
    - Victorian Poetic Drama (Box-folder 43:14)
    - Vocation of the Theatre (literary lecture) (Box-folder 43:15)
    - What Women Most Desire (lecture related to Chaucer) (Box-folder 43:16)
    - Art Institute lecture given 2/17/54 (Box-folder 43:16)
    - Cleveland Book Fair lecture given November 1953 (Box-folder 43:17)
    - Farmville Waterworks lecture (not dated) (Box-folder 43:18)
    - Geist Tapping Ceremony of 1/19/78 (Box-folder 43:19)
    - VEA Conference lecture (not dated) (Box-folder 43:20)
    - Virginia Federation of Women's Club lecture given 4/25/72 (Box-folder 43:21)
    - Unidentified - 2 lectures (Box-folder 43:22)
    - Collection of stories, plays, and essays written by Sprague during her school and college years (Boxr 44)
    - Book covers and oversize galley proofs. Galley Proof for Forever in Joy Galley Proof for Poems of Robert Browning Galley Proof for George Eliot Galley Proof for Dance for a Diamond Star Galley Proof for Imaginary Gardens (fragment of work) Galley Proof for A Kingdom to Win Feb. 1950 Galley Proof for Jade Pagoda Cover for Dance for a Diamond Star Cover for George Eliot Cover for Heroes of the White Shield Illustration – Map of Viking Kingdom of Garderik (Box 45)
- Series 3: Personal and Biographical - Photograph Collection
  - Personal and Biographical
    - Certificate of Baptism and Related Documents (Box-folder 46:1)
    - College Acceptance Papers (Box-folder 46:2)
    - Academic Transcripts and Related Documents (Box-folder 46:3)
    - Commencement Program - June 1941 (Box-folder 46:4)
    - Playbills/Scripts for Events w/ Sprague's Involvement (Box-folder 46:5-6)
    - Special Awards - CHI Recognition and AAUW Award (Box-folder 46:7)
    - BOV Distinguished Professor Award 1967 (Box-folder 46:8)
    - Miller and Rhoads Book Author Dinner 1973-74 Program and Letter of Thanks (Box-folder 46:9)
    - Parlour Entertainment Information (literacy benefit) 1990 (Box-folder 46:10)
    - Reviews of and Ads for Publications (Box-folder 46:11)
    - Information Pertaining to Mother's Funeral Service (Box-folder 46:12)
    - Information Pertaining to Father's Death and Funeral Service (Box-folder 46:13)
    - Information Related to the Sprague Family (Box-folder 46:14-19)
    - Autobiographical Writing -Life After Hathaway Brown (Box-folder 46:20)
    - Johns Memorial Church Services – programs and readings (Box-folder 46:21)
    - Newspaper Articles about Dr. Sprague - 1935-1963 (Box-folder 47:1)
    - Newspaper Articles about Dr. Sprague - 1963-1986 (Box-folder 47:2)
    - Reviews of Sprague Publications (Box-folder 47:3-13)
    - Articles Related to Appearances and Lectures (Box-folder 47:14)
    - Collection of Contracts and Royalty Statements
      - Miscellaneous Contract Agreements (Box-folder 48:1)
      - Author-Publisher Agreements (Box-folder 48:2-3)
      - Author's Guild Agreements (Box-folder 48:4)
      - Royalty Statements (Box-folder 48:5-6)
      - Bank Statements from Walck Royalty (Box-folder 48:7)
      - Bank Statements from Crowell Royalty (Box-folder 48:8)
      - Bank Statements on book sales from Chilton Books (Box-folder 48:9)
  - Photographs
    - Family Photographs #1, 1920-1929 (Box-folder 49:1)
    - Family Photographs#2, 1920-1929 (Box-folder 49:2)
    - Slides of family trips (Box-folder 49:3)
    - Smaller Photographs of Rosemary Sprague (Box-folder 49:4)
    - Smaller Photographs of Father, Percy Sprague (Box-folder 49:5)
    - Negatives of photographs (Box-folder 49:6)
    - Negatives of photographs #2 (Box-folder 49:7)
    - Clippings Concerning Rosemary Sprague in School and in Theater (Box-folder 49:8)
    - Signed photographs from actors and actresses #1 (Box-folder 49:9)
    - Signed photographs from actors and actresses #2 (Box-folder 49:10)
    - Photographs from various plays in which Rosemary Sprague performed (Box-folder 49:11)
    - Postcards collected from Travels (Box-folder 49:12)
    - Photographs of Rosemary Sprague's trips around Europe (Box-folder 49:13)
    - Photographs of Sprague and Her Dog (Box-folder 49:14)
    - Photographs of Rosemary Sprague's Funeral (Box-folder 49:15)
  - Miscellaneous Photos
    - Small Miscellaneous Photographs (Box-folder 50:1)
    - Small Miscellaneous Photographs #2 (Box-folder 50:2)
    - Medium Miscellaneous Photographs (Box-folder 50:3)
    - Miscellaneous Small Photographs - early 1900s (Box-folder 50:4)
    - Miscellaneous Medium Photographs - early 1900s (Box-folder 50:5)
    - Miscellaneous Medium Photographs - early 1900s #2 (Box-folder 50:6)
    - Miscellaneous Large Photos - early 1900s (Box-folder 50:7)
    - Miscellaneous photographs from Album (Box-folder 50:8)
  - Oversized Photos and One Framed Letter written by Robert Browning (Box 51)
- Series 4: Miscellaneous Collection
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera and Collectible Print Materials
    - Business Cards (Box-folder 52:1)
    - Postcards, collectibles (Box-folder 52:2)
    - Papers written by Dr. Sprague's students (Box-folder 52:3)
    - Paperwork regarding Oscar Williams (Box-folder 52:4)
    - Playbills/Scripts for Plays (Box-folder 52:5)
    - Professional Stills of Shakespearean Plays (Box-folder 52:6)
    - Programs of church services (Box-folder 52:7)
    - Manhattan Theatre Colony brochure (Box-folder 52:8)
    - Programs of special events (Box-folder 52:9)
    - Editorial written by Sprague's Father (Box-folder 52:10)
    - Items given to Rosemary Sprague regarding literature and art (keepsakes) (Box-folder 52:11)
    - Golden Keys Book List (Box-folder 52:12)
  - Miscellaneous Class Notes
    - English 120 Notes (Box-folder 53:1)
    - Fun with Hamlet (Box-folder 53:2)
    - Three Little Pigs (Box-folder 53:3)
    - Shakespearean Definitions (Box-folder 53:4)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #1 (Box-folder 53:5-6)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #2 (Box-folder 53:7-8)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #3 (Box-folder 53:9)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #4 (Box-folder 53:10)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #5 (Box-folder 53:11-12)
  - Miscellaneous Class Notes - continued
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #6 (Box-folder 54:1-6)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #7 (Box-folder 54:7-11)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #8 (Box-folder 54:12)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #9 (Box-folder 54:13)
    - Miscellaneous Class Notes #10 (Box-folder 54:14)
  - Miscellaneous Class Notes - continued
    - French Class Notes (Box-folder 55:1)
    - History Class Notes (Box-folder 55:2)
    - Random class notes and writings (Box-folder 55:3)
  - Miscellaneous Collection of Articles, Magazines and Print Items
    - Miscellaneous notes of history-related topics (Box-folder 56:1)
    - Richmond Shakespeare Lecture Notes (Box-folder 56:1)
    - Copy of To Christ I Look #1 (Box-folder 56:2)
    - Copy of To Christ I Look #2 (Box-folder 56:3)
    - Copy of paper titled 16th Century Book of Common Prayer (Box-folder 56:4)
    - Poetry Clippings (Box-folder 56:5-6)
  - Large Box of Personal and Miscellaneous Items (Box-folder 57:1-10)
  - Large Box of Personal and Miscellaneous Items (box contains both three-dimensional items and large print items (Box 58)
    - Chi Commendation from 1976 (Box-folder 58:1)
    - Set of Business Cards for Rosemary Sprague as Professor at Longwood College (Box-folder 58:2)
    - Box of Miniature Photographs of Landscapes (Box-folder 58:3)
    - Unmarked Postcards from around the world (Box-folder 58:4)
    - "Black Diamond" Magazine with Article on the Death of Mr. Percy Sprague; Large Photo of Coal Mine
    - Longwood College Faculty Colloquium "Distinguished Professor Award," 1984
    - Longwood College Faculty Colloquium "Distinguished Professor Award," 1989
    - "Kate Greenaway's Birthday Bash Book" with birthdays listed inside (2)
    - Wooden Box with "Tempe Date Gardens" pictured on Lid
    - Framed Article on Retirement of Dr. Stephen Joseph Herben
    - Used Address Book
    - Tin Box from England
    - Metal Bookmark from Catholic Church in Korea, "RS" inscribed on it
    - Handkerchief with Needlework on it "A Soft Answer Turneth Away Wrath"
    - Holy Bible (2)
    - Prayer Book with inscription from parents on front page
    - Copy of "Payne's Social Letter Writer for Ladies and Gentlemen"
    - Framed Photo of Rosemary Sprague as a young adult
    - The Metropolitan Museum of Art: Calendar for 1960 - A Cloisters Bestiary
    - The Metropolitan Museum of Art: Calendar for 1966 - A Medieval Treasury
    - Small Black Photo Album with Photos in it
    - Framed Silhouette of Rosemary Sprague
  - This large box contains unprocessed notes, research, and writings related to Longwood College: A History. (Box 59)